Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is קכא, kuf chaf
aleph, 121. And we pick up at the top of קכא, kuf
chaf aleph, three lines from the top or four... רבי יהודה אומר
לא כל. Rabbi Yehuda Omer Lo Kol. So Rabbi Yehuda says this
is an issue about identifying somebody, and Rabbi Yehuda said that you
can't, not all...
and the משנה mishna said that you have three days and afterwards
you're concerned that the body will like bloat and won't be identifiable,
so you cannot go on identify... you can identify it after three
days. And Rabbi Yehuda said not all the, you know, not all
people are the same, not all conditions are the same, and you
can't make any strict rules. So the גמרא Gemara says איבעיא להו,
Ibeilu, they asked the question: רבי יהודה בן בבא, Rabbi Yehuda ben
Baba, לקולא פליגי או לחומרא פליגי? likula pligi o lechumra pligi? Is
he being lenient or strict? Of course תוספות Tosafos points out the
easy answer is neither or both. He's saying like it's not like
you can go less than three, you know, it's strict is that
you can't identify even in less than three days, lenient is you
can identify even in more. But the point is, maybe he's saying
there's no rule, sometimes it's less, sometimes it's more.
So I know the גמרא Gemara says so. It's fixed...
and it's fixed the throat? Yeah, exactly, exactly. So תא שמע, Tashma,
come and hear. דהוא גברא דטבע בכרמי, Dehu gavra detava becharmi, a
certain person drowned in a place called Charmi. ואסקוהו בחדייא, Vaskua be-chadya,
and they lifted and they raised up his body in this place
be-chadya לבתר תלתא יומין, Lebasar tlosa yomin, after three days. ואנסבה רב
דימי מנהרדעא
לדביתהו, Ve-ansva Rav Dimi min Naharda'ei lidevayeihu, and Rav Dimi min Nahardai
identified him and allowed his wife to marry. ותו, V'tu, in addition,
דהוא גברא דטבע בדגלת, dihu gavra de'atva be-Diglas, a certain person drowned
in Diglas, which is the Tigris. ואסקוהו אגישרא דשביסתנא, Vasku be-gisra de-shavistana,
and they lifted up his body by the bridge of Shavistana. ואנסבה
רבא לדביתהו, Ve-ansva Rava lidevayeihu, and Rava allowed his wife to marry
אפומא דשושביני, apumei de-shushvini, by based on the testimony of the groomsman
לבתר חמישה יומי, Lebasar chamisha yomi,
after five days, meaning his good friends identified him and it was
five days later. אי אמרת בשלמא לקולא פליגי, Ei amart bishlama likula
pligi, if Rabbi Yehuda is lenient and that you can identify it
after three days, היינו דעבדי כרבי יהודה בן בבא, inu d'avid ke-Rabbi
Yehuda ben Baba, they're ruling like him. אלא אמרת לחומרא פליגי, Ela
amart lechumra pligi, but if he's strict, he says three days is
the max, sometimes even less than three days you can't identify, אינהו
דעבדי כמאן, inu d'avid k'man, who are they going like? So you
see Rabbi Yehuda at least would allow his position to be more
lenient. Maybe sometimes he'd be more strict, but at least here times
he'd be more lenient because he's willing to look at each case
individually. So the גמרא Gemara says: שאני מיא דצמתי, shani maye d'tsamtei,
water is different because water shrivels, and therefore it's after somebody has
drowned, it's easier, you can have more time to identify. So meaning
maybe they're even going like the חכמים Chachamim that say three days,
but you get an extension if the guy drowned, which is of
course so funny because that's Rabbi Yehuda's approach. He says you can't
make any strict rules, you have to look at the circumstances. But
maybe they feel well, drowning like if you could make a formal
category that if the guy drowned, you know, then he has more
time. That's different than just having absolutely no rules to say like,
well always assess it case by case. Of course the also funny
thing is that you know most of the time you assume if
somebody is drowned it's a lot harder to identify the body, you
know. So to say that it's easier, you know, if he drowned
is so funny. So the
גמרא Gemara says: ואמרת מיא מרזו מכה,
Ve-amart
maya
marzu maka, we said yesterday that water exacerbates a wound and therefore,
you know, even wounds that might not have been considered fatal will
be in water. Of course what does that have to do with
identifying is not exactly the same. Yeah, הני מילי היכא דאיכא מכה,
hani milei heicha de'ika maka, that's where there's a wound. אבל היכא
דליכא מכה, Aval heicha deleika maka, but if there's no wound, מצמת
צמית, mitsmat tsamit, and it'll shrivel it and maybe it'll allow it
to be identified even later. So the גמרא Gemara says: והני מילי
דכי אסקי חזייא בשעתא, ve-hani milei dehachi aska chazi besha'atei,
that's only if when they lifted took him out of the water
they saw him immediately. אבל אישתהי, Aval ishtahi, if they waited before
looking at the body, מתפח טפח, mitpach tapach, then it will bloat
afterwards and then it's no longer identifiable. So the גמרא Gemara doesn't
really conclude which way Rabbi Yehuda is saying, obviously logically he's saying
both ways. But it also says that even the רבנן Rabbanan who
say three days should not be interpreted as a strict and absolute
standard. Okay, next משנה. mishna. Now we get to a classic distinction...
oh I don't know... now we get to a classic... I mean
we're always trying to find opportunities to be, you know, lenient in
this case, as we already saw in the earlier discussion about סימנים.
simanim. So I assume... okay. Now we get to an important distinction
between מים שיש להם סוף mayim she-yesh lahem sof and מים שאין
להם סוף. mayim she'ein lahem sof. Let's take a look. נפל למים
בין שיש להם סוף בין שאין להם סוף. Nafal lemayim bein she-yesh
lahem sof bein she'ein lahem sof.
If a guy fell into water, whether there's an end to the
water or not. Of course there's always an end, we live in
a finite world, but it means whether you can see the shores,
okay?
And the idea being that if the shores are visible of all
around, then it's easier to marry off his wife. Why? You would
think אדרבה, adaraba, if the shores are visible he could have swum
to shore and he could have survived. But the point is then
you would have seen him. If the shore is not visible, then
it's possible you never saw him and he emerged somewhere where it
wasn't visible. He emerged
beyond your, you
know, beyond the horizon, beyond where you are.
Right,
and a river would always in a way be אין להם סוף
ein lahem sof because you would never, right, how would you ever
be able to see the other end? That's a very good point.
So the Gemara says, so the Mishnah says, נפל למים בין שיש
להם סוף בין שאין להם סוף אשתו אסורה. Nafal lemayim bein sheyeish
lahem sof bein she'ein lahem sof ishto asurah. So the first position
is, and we'll see it's going to follow with an אמר רבי
מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, but in the Gemara it'll be clear from
a Brayta that this is the position of Rabbi Meir. That Rabbi
Meir basically says you can never testify if you don't see a
body. Right? So even if it's יש להם סוף yeish lahem sof
and you could say, well, I would have seen him emerge from
the shore, Rabbi Meir says, tough luck! If he drowned in the
river and you never saw a body, you can never testify. אמר
רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, Rabbi Meir said, מעשה באחד שנפל לבור
גדול, ma'aseh be'echad shenafal levor gadol,
a certain person fell into a deep well, ועלה לאחר שלושה ימים,
ve'alah le'achar sheloshah yamim,
and he came up after three days. So if you don't see
a body you can never know. So what's that movie, 127 hours
or something? What was it?
127 hours. 127 hours, so there you go. That was more, that
was what, six days? Right,
oh yeah, wow. Okay, so it's possible that, you know, that
if
you don't see a body you never know. The guy might have
survived. That's Rabbi Meir's position. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yosi, Rabbi
Yosi disagrees. מעשה, Ma'aseh,
it's interesting he doesn't say his halakhic position but he just tells
a story. מעשה בסומא שירד לטבול במערה, Ma'aseh besuma sheyarad litbol beme'arah,
a certain blind person went down to immerse in a cave, וירד
מושכו אחריו, veyarad moshkho acharav,
and somebody apparently was lowering him down by a rope and then
he went down after him. Maybe he went down to find out
what was wrong with him or maybe he was pulled down by
the rope. ושהו כדי שתצא נפשם, Veshahu kedei sheteitzei nafsham,
and the Rabbis waited the time it would take for them to
die down there without food or water or air, whatever their assessment
was. והשיאו את נשותיהם, Vehisi'u et neshooteihem, and they let their wives
remarry. So you see that you're wrong Rabbi Meir, that we will
allow people to marry even without a body. ושוב מעשה באסיא, Veshuv
ma'aseh be'Asya, there was a story we quoted this before in Asia,
באחד ששלשלוהו לים, be'echad sheshilshuluhu layam,
they lowered somebody down to do some deep sea diving, ולא עלתה
בידם אלא רגלו, velo altah beyadam ella raglo,
and they only were able to lift up his leg. אמרו חכמים,
Amru chakhamim, and the sages say, מן הארכובה ולמעלה, min ha'arkuvah ule'ma'lah,
if the leg was severed above the knee, תינשא, tinasei, then he
definitely has died. מן הארכובה ולמטה, Min ha'arkuvah ule'matah, if it was
severed below the knee, לא תינשא. lo tinasei. Now the last point
is not really relevant because the last point you have evidence that
he has a wound and it might be a fatal wound. That's
very different than the other cases where you don't know the person
was wounded, you just assume he died and you didn't see a
body. Okay, and that's really the debate of Rabbi Meir and Rabbi
Yosi: can you assume somebody died without actually having seen a body?
So let's take a look at the Gemara. תנו רבנן: Tanu rabanan:
נפל למים בין שיש להם סוף בין שאין להם סוף אשתו אסורה
דברי רבי מאיר. Nafal lemayim bein sheyeish lahem sof bein she'ein lahem
sof ishto asurah divrei Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Meir says if he drowned,
his wife is forbidden. No body, you cannot pronounce him dead. וחכמים
אומרים, Vachakhamim omrim, and the sages say, מים שיש להם סוף אשתו
מותרת. mayim sheyeish lahem sof ishto muteret.
If the water has an edge and you could have seen the
edge and watched and seen if he would have, if he would
have, you know, come out, then and he didn't come out, then
on the basis of not seeing him come out you can marry
off his wife. ושאין להם סוף, Veshe'ein lahem sof, but if there
is no edge to the water, then אשתו אסורה, ishto asurah, his
wife is forbidden, because you don't know, maybe he emerged somewhere else.
היכי דמי מים שיש להם סוף? Heikhi dami mayim sheyeish lahem sof?
What would be an example that there's an edge? How do you
define that? אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, כל שעומד ורואה מארבע רוחותיו. kol
she'omed vero'eh me'arba ruchotav.
Any place where you could stand and see in all four directions,
you could see the, like, the edges of the water. But if
you know the shores on all four sides. But even on one
side you can't, then you don't know, maybe that's the side he
emerged from. Okay,
so now the Gemara's going to have some story. ההוא גברא דטבע
באגמא, Hahu gavra detava be'agma, a certain person drowned in a swamp,
דסמקי, deSamki, that was
like red or some...
normally סומק sumak is red... Rashi says it's the name of a
place, excuse me, the swamp of Samki. אינסבה רב שילה לדביתהו, Insavah
Rav Shila lidveiteihu, Rav
Shila allowed his wife to marry. He assumed it was שיש להם
סוף yeish lahem sof because, well we'll see in the Gemara.
אמר ליה רב לשמואל, Amar lei Rav liShmuel, תא נשמתיה, ta nishmateih,
let's go put him in חרם cherem because, put him in שמתא
shamta because he married off the wife even though this was a
case of שאין להם סוף, she'ein lahem sof, so we have to
censure him. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so Shmuel said, no no
no, נשלח ליה ברישא, nishlach lei bereisha, let's first send him a
message, let's first investigate the case a little bit before we rush
to put him in
חרם. cherem. נשלח ליה ברישא. Nishlach lei bereisha. שלחו ליה: Shalchu lei:
מים שאין להם סוף אשתו אסורה או מותרת? Mayim she'ein lahem sof
ishto asurah o muteret? Water that has no edge, what do you
think the halakhah is? Is the halakhah that his wife is permissible
or forbidden? שלח להו: Shalach lehu: אשתו אסורה, Ishto asurah, his wife
is forbidden.
ואגמא דסמקי, Ve'agma deSamki, and then they sent him again or whatever,
was it same time, and the swamp of Samki, מים שיש להם
סוף או מים שאין להם סוף? mayim sheyeish lahem sof o mayim
she'ein lahem sof? What is it? Is
it... So then they said, okay, so you admit to the principle
that אין להם סוף ein lahem sof you can't marry his wife.
And you admit that this water is considered אין להם סוף. ein
lahem sof. So מר מאי טעמא עבד הכי, mar mai ta'ama avad
hachi, why did you marry off his wife? So he said, מיטע
טעינא, mita te'ina, you know what? I made a mistake. אנא סברי,
ana savri, I assumed, כיון דקאי וקיימי kivan d'ka'i v'kaimi כמים שיש
להם סוף דמי. k'mayim sheyeish lahem sof dami. It's true, it's a
huge swamp, you can't see the edges of it. But on the
other hand, the water is stable, it's a swamp, there's no moving
water. So I assumed that if it was stable water,
then no matter how far it went, you know, you wouldn't say
he got swept by the undercurrent and emerged somewhere else. You would
say if he survived, you would have seen him come up somewhere
near where he went under because it's standing water. It was a
very reasonable assumption. So, I
assumed כיון דקאי וקיימי kivan d'ka'i v'kaimi כמים שיש להם סוף דמי.
k'mayim sheyeish lahem sof dami. ולא היא, v'lo hi, it's not true.
כיון דאיכא גלי, kivan d'ika gali, since there are waves, again I
don't know what type of a swamp it is that has waves,
since there are some type, there is some type of currents let's
say, so אימור גלי אשפלוהו, eimar gali ashpluhu, maybe the waves carried
him under. Of course, the funny thing is is that how does
he realize he made a mistake? Like you know, maybe because they're
challenging him you realize oh wait, maybe you're assessing this differently than
I am, but you know what made him say he made a
mistake? They just said, why did you say she was מותרת? mutteres?
And he said I said she was מותרת mutteres because I assumed
it has, you know, why did he say it's considered אין להם
סוף? ein lahem sof? When they asked him is it אין להם
סוף ein lahem sof or יש להם סוף? yeish lahem sof? He
should have said it's יש להם סוף yeish lahem sof because it's
standing water. So somewhere along the way he realized that they did
not approve of his פסק. psak. So he sort of reversed himself
as a result of the questioning and realized that he had, you
know, misjudged it.
Wait, I can clarify for a second. Still water in a swamp
doesn't have swept-under water currents, but sometimes the wind alone blowing on
the surface of the water is able to generate waves. So that's
how the waves came in. Okay.
All right.
But at least it says it's got underwater currents, which makes sense.
What happened to the water?
So let's take a look.
So קרי שמואל עליה דרב, kari Shmuel alei d'Rav, so שמואל Shmuel
then said for רב Rav because רב Rav was going to put
him in שמתא shamta and they actually discovered that they shouldn't put
him in שמתא shamta because even though he made a mistake, you
don't put somebody in שמתא shamta because he made a mistake. You
put somebody in שמתא shamta for sort of like, you know, willfully
violating our, you know, the rules. And so therefore this person did
not sort of, you know, fly in the face of the הלכה.
halakha. He made a mistake. People do make mistakes. You don't put
them in שמתא. shamta. You put them in שמתא shamta if somebody's
like just willfully stepping out of bounds, right? So therefore they decided
not to put him in שמתא. shamta. קרי שמואל עליה דרב, kari
Shmuel alei d'Rav, so שמואל Shmuel said about רב: Rav: לא יאונה
לצדיק כל און. lo ye'uneh latzadik kol aven. So to a righteous
person no bad thing will happen because you were going to put
him in שמתא, shamta, it wouldn't have been justified, it was an
honest mistake, and that wouldn't look bad on you that you would
have put him in שמתא, shamta, so it's a good thing you
got saved from that. So קרי רב עליה דשמואל, kari Rav alei
d'Shmuel, so רב Rav said about שמואל: Shmuel: ותשועה ברוב יועץ, v'teshuah
b'rov yoetz, salvation comes from good advice. So thank you שמואל Shmuel
for giving me the advice for first checking it out before I
went out and acted on it. It wasn't this deus ex machina
that I didn't do it, you helped me out. Okay. The funny
thing is of course we'll ask, so now what happened to this
woman? Right? She got married on the basis of this. He realized
he made a mistake. So we're going to see in the end
that actually בדיעבד, bedi'eved, even in a case of מים שאין להם
סוף, mayim she'ein lahem sof, if the woman got a פסק psak
and got married, she can stay married. So that's actually an interesting
point which we don't realize now, certainly not at all clear from
the משנה. Mishna. Okay, but what is interesting in this story is
you don't hear, okay, good, he wasn't put in חרם cherem and
nobody did any, you know, nobody made any conscious error or whatever.
Fine. But what about the woman? So we're going to find out
that בדיעבד bedi'eved the woman is okay.
Yeah, but this is a question about when he turns out alive.
He's not turning out alive. It's just that you פסקן pasken based
on and there's still a concern that maybe he survived, right? But
you don't have, you know, the evidence isn't black and white. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
תניא, tanya, we learned a ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי, amar Rabbi, said
רבי: Rabbi: מעשה בשני בני אדם ma'aseh bishnei b'nei adam מכמרי
מכמורין michammrei michmorin בירדן. ba'Yarden. There's a story about two people that
were casting fishing nets in the Jordan. ונתלה אחד מהם למחילה של
דגים, v'nitla echad meihem l'mechilah shel dagim, and one of them went
into an underground sort of cavern, you know, cave of fish or
a tunnel where there are fish.
ושקעה חמה v'shaka chamah ולא ראה פתחה של מחילה. v'lo ra'ah pitchah
shel mechilah. And the sun set and he could not see the
exit of the tunnel.
ושהה חבירו כדי שתצא נפשו, v'shaha chaveiro k'dei sheteitzei nafsho, and his
friend sort of waited long enough, figured the guy never came out,
he's definitely dead. ובא והודיע בתוך ביתו, u'va v'hodia b'toch beito, and
they told his wife: your husband drowned. למחר, l'machar, in the next
morning, זרחה חמה, zarcha chamah, the sun shone, והכיר פתחה של מחילה,
v'hikir pitchah shel mechilah, and he was able to see the opening
of the cave. ובא ומצא, u'va u'matza, and he came to his
town and he found הספד גדול בתוך ביתו, hesped gadol b'toch beito,
there's a big eulogy going out, right, going on in his house.
אמר, amar, so anyway now רש"י Rashi says that it's a type
of a cave where there was like a little space of air,
you know, there were air pockets or something. So אמר, amar, he
said, אמר רבי, amar Rabbi, כמה גדולים דברי חכמים, kamah gedolim divrei
chachamim, how great are the words of
the
sages, שאמרו. she'amru. but ultimately there was a they weren't able you
know to detect now of course the point is that as the
גמרא Gemara is going to say even if it's a case exactly
the גמרא Gemara is going to say that even if it was
a case of יש להם סוף yesh lahem sof maybe he got
maybe he was you know he'll find these air pockets and so
what does it have to do with יש להם סוף yesh lahem
sof or אין להם סוף ein lahem sof it doesn't have to
do with seeing the edge it has to do with finding a
little cave underground that has air pockets so let's take a look
what the גמרא Gemara says okay אי
הכי
i
hachee
says the גמרא Gemara מים שיש להם סוף נמי mayim she-yeish lahem
sof nami so even if it's even if it's a case with
water that has an edge ליחוש למחילה של דגין leichosh lemchila shel
dagin
so let's be afraid that there's like a a tunnel with fish
meaning with air pockets so no גמרא Gemara says מים שיש להם
סוף מחילה של דגין לא שכיחי mayim she-yeish lahem sof mechila shel
dagin lo shchichi that type of water that has an edge that's
not a huge ocean those types of underground caverns are not common
okay so it's a little funny because now we're just you know
they're not really it's not really about whether you can see the
edge or not it's of a vast body of water it's sort
of saying like you don't know what's going to happen in a
vast body of water and maybe there'll be these underground tunnels but
of course again it's pretty funny and as Dov pointed out if
you're talking about a river so that's always אין להם סוף ein
lahem sof cause it's always going like away from you you know
you always don't see the the you know the end of the
river all right anyway so that was
a good thing it
has to be from all four sides and although the גמרא Gemara
is acknowledging that even then sometimes there'll be ways that people can
reach to escape we're not going to be afraid of it אמר
רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi הא דאמרו רבנן מים שאין להם סוף
hada amru rabanan mayim she-ein lahem sof by the way you notice
that רב מאיר Rav Meir has totally been forgotten about right we're
totally assuming that if it's אין להם סוף ein lahem sof you
if it's יש להם סוף yesh lahem sof you can marry off
his wife אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi הא דאמרו רבנן מים
שאין להם סוף אשתו אסורה hada amru rabanan mayim she-ein lahem sof
ishto asura that which we say that when it's אין להם סוף
ein lahem sof the wife is forbidden הני מילי באיניש דעלמא hani
mili be-inish de-alma
that's only and so we're already we're going to see like a
constant you know cutting away of the or let me reframe it
you know a constant broadening of the cases where you can believe
that his wife
is dead the first one is we פסקן pasken against רב מאיר
Reb Meir if it's יש להם סוף yesh lahem sof even without
a body you can testify now we're going to say even if
it's אין להם סוף ein lahem sof הא דאמרו רבנן
מים שאין להם סוף אשתו אסורה הני מילי באיניש דעלמא hada amru
rabanan mayim she-ein lahem sof ishto asura hani mili be-inish de-alma that's
if the guy who died was a normal guy אבל צורבא מרבנן
aval tzurba me-rabanan if he was a תורה Torah sage whoa then
you can testify even if it's אין להם סוף ein lahem sof
which is pretty shocking right why should he be more assumed to
be dead אי דסליק e d'salik because him if he came up
like you know three cities away you know or a hundred miles
away if he if he survived קלא אית ליה kala is lei
there would have been a report there would have been sound about
it he's an important person so important people if they drown right
then and then then we can assume if we haven't heard about
them surviving even if we there was even if there was no
edge to the water we can assume they didn't survive cause else
we would have heard about it the גמרא Gemara says ולא היא
velo hee that's not true לא שנא איניש דעלמא ולא שנא צורבא
מרבנן lo shnei inish de-alma velo shnei tzurba me-rabanan it doesn't matter
a normal person doesn't matter a תורה Torah sage or a famous
person
בדיעבד bedi'eved yes if you if and that's what i mentioned to
you before again this is not at all in the משנה Mishnah
this is a big surprise that the גמרא Gemara just introduces without
any discussion בדיעבד bedi'eved if you married off the wife even in
a case where there's no body and there's no edge to the
water she can stay married לכתחילה לא le-chatchila lo you can't do
it לכתחילה le-chatchila so again in addition to פסקנינג paskening not like
רב מאיר Reb Meir the גמרא Gemara just you know in passing
drops in this fact that oh by the way if she did
get married she can stay married even even with no body even
if there's no edge to the water
so is he kind of telling her you know like practically as
a בית דין beis din you come to us we can't tell
you you can but if you
do you know can
is that i
don't know it's a good question
בדיעבד bedi'eved be like the case we had before where there's the
the בית דין beis din or the rabbi made a mistake as
opposed
to when she willfully went ahead okay that's an interesting case so
let's take a look at at the another case that's going to
come up okay there's going to be a case of לכתחילה le-chatchila
and בדיעבד bedi'eved coming up let's take a look תניא tanya we
taught in a ברייתא Baraisa אמר רבן גמליאל Amar Rabban Gamliel פעם
אחת הייתי מהלך בספינה pa'am achas hayiti mehalech bisefina
once i was going on on a boat וראיתי ספינה אחת ve-ra'iti
sefina achas and i saw another boat שנשברה she-nishbera that had was
shipwrecked והייתי מצטער על תלמיד חכם שבה ve-hayiti mitzta'er al talmid chacham
she-ba
and i was concerned about you know about a great תורה Torah
sage that was on that ship ומנו רבי עקיבא umannu Rabbi Akiva
who was it it was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva it's interesting wasn't
he concerned also about everybody else okay in particular i was also
concerned about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva וכשעליתי ליבשה ve-cheshelis'i bayabasha
when my ship docked בא וישב ודן לפני בהלכה ba veyashav vedan
lefanai behalacha there was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and he wanted to
have a Halachic discussion with me אמרתי לו amarti lo i said
to him בני מי העלך beni mi he'elcha my son who who
got you out of the ocean i saw your ship was shipwrecked
אמר לי amar li he said to me דף של ספינה נזדמן
לי daf shel sefina nizdamen li there was a plank from the
ship that floated my way וכל גל וגל שבא
עלי ve-chol gal ve-gal she-ba alai and every wave, yeah, just excuse
me a second, this is work-related,
hold on one second.
Okay, so and every and every and every and every wave that
came my way, וכל גל וגל שבא עלי, ve-chol gal ve-gal she-ba
alai, נענעתי לו
ראשי,
naaneti
lo roshi, I bent my head so the wave would pass over
me and I wouldn't be hit by the force of the wave.
And by the way, of course, what good story, you know, what
good is this tremendous experience unless you could use it for a
sermon? So therefore, מכאן אמרו חכמים, mikan amru chachamim, from here the
sages said, אם יבואו רשעים על אדם, im yavo'u resha'im al adam,
if wicked people come to attack a person, ינענע לו ראשו, yenane'a
lo rosho, bend down your head, you know, don't stand up to
powerful wicked people, let them, you know, discretion is the better part
of valor or something. So that's the משל mashal of bending your
head so the wave passes over you. Okay. אמרתי, amarti, anyway, back
to our point, באותה שעה, be-ota sha'a, I said at that time,
says רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, כמה גדולים דברי חכמים שאמרו מים שיש
להם סוף מותרת מים שאין להם סוף אסורה. kama gedolim divrei chachamim
she-amru mayim she-yesh lahem sof muteret mayim she-ein lahem sof asura. How
great is it when they said that if the water has no
edges the wife is forbidden because there was a shipwreck in the
middle of the ocean and of course I assumed he was totally
dead but who would be able to see that somewhere where the
eye couldn't see he was on a plank and he managed to
survive and you couldn't see the edge of the water. Okay. So
similarly, תניא, tanya, which is in a ברייתא, Braita, אמר רבי עקיבא,
amar Rabbi Akiva, פעם אחת הייתי מהלך בספינה, pa'am achat hayiti mahalech
bis-fina, once I was going in a boat, וראיתי ספינה אחת שמטרפת
בים, ve-ra'iti se-fina achat she-mitarefet ba-yam,
and I saw a boat that was sort of, if not shipwrecked,
it was being cast about in the sea. והייתי מצטער על תלמיד
חכם שבה, ve-hayiti mitzta'er al talmid chacham she-bah, and I was afraid
for a Torah sage that was on it. ומנו, u-manu, and who
was it? רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. כשהעליתי למדינת קפוטקיא, kesh-haliti le-medinat Kaputkia,
it's always their תלמיד talmid that's on the boat, when I went
when I finally למדינת קפוטקיא, le-medinat Kaputkia, then I finally
docked at the קפוטקיא, Kaputkia, what's קפוטקיא? Kaputkia? Cappadocia, whatever that is.
Anyway, בא וישב ודן לפני בהלכה, ba ve-yashav ve-dan lefanai be-halacha, there
was רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir and he was having a halachic discussion with me.
אמרתי לו, amarti lo, I said to him, בני מי העלך, beni
mi helcha, who got you out of the ocean? אמר לי, amar
li, he said to me, גל טרדני לחברו
וחברו לחברו, gal tardani le-chavero ve-chavero le-chavero, one wave cast me to
the next wave and from one wave to the next to the
next to the next, עד שהקיאני ליבשה, ad she-hikiani la-yabasha, until
finally I was cast out onto the dry land. אמרתי, amarti, I
said, באותה שעה, be-ota sha'a, כמה גדולים דברי חכמים שאמרו מים שיש
להם סוף אישה מותרת מים שאין להם סוף אישה אסורה. kama gedolim
divrei chachamim she-amru mayim she-yesh lahem sof isha muteret mayim she-ein lahem
sof isha asura.
You see, ברוך ה', Baruch Hashem, sometimes people can survive but because
ברוך ה' Baruch Hashem sometimes people can survive, you know, therefore we
have to be more hesitant before marrying off a woman and so
therefore you cannot do it if there is no you cannot see
the edge of the water.
קפוטקיא Kaputkia is כפתור, Kaftor, כפתורי דהיינו כפתור. Kaftori de-hainu Kaftor. Yeah,
and it's in modern-day Turkey. Modern-day Turkey.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan.
This must have been a major
event in the life of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, right? That we
only find out about it, you know, right, as an aside the
water dripping on
the
rock,
that's something that is being
worked forward than the גמרא Gemara and various other things
but, yeah, it's a good point, yeah, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva survived
the shipwreck and was sort of sort of holding on to a
plank, you know, maybe he was on the ocean for three for
three months for all we know. And that we don't hear about
except in passing in this story, right?
So on the other hand, it's hard to take the story seriously
because of all the repetitions.
Yeah, I mean it's right, it does sound like a bit of
a like of a trope here, so that's
true. Anyway, תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, it's a good very good point.
נפל לגוב אריות, nafal le-gov arayot, somebody was like relived a Daniel
story and fell into a pit of
lions, אין מעידים עליו, ein me'idim alav, you can't testify that he
died, you know, maybe he managed to tame the lions, maybe as
רש"י Rashi says maybe the lions weren't hungry that day. I don't
know, is that really true? Like if you don't if you don't
antagonize lions and they're not hungry will they not attack you? Does
anybody know? Let's check. Safari experience.
I mean, like, a lot of these lions were like among millions
of wildebeest
and they weren't attacking
them because like they just they'd just eaten like before, right? Okay.
אין מעידים עליו.
ein me'idim
alav. לחפורה מלאה נחשים ועקרבים, le-chafura me-le'a ne-chashim va-akrabim,
if it's a well filled with snakes and scorpions, like a pit,
מעידים עליו, me'idim alav, then they definitely will attack him. So that's
an Indiana Jones scenario. Yeah, right.
רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר אף
לחפורה מלאה נחשים ועקרבים אין מעידים עליו,
Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer
af le-chafura
me-le'a ne-chashim va-akrabim ein me'idim alav,
even in that case you can't testify he died, why? חיישינן, chaishinan,
we're afraid שמא חבר הוא, she-ma chaver hu,
maybe he is a חבר chaver which is somebody that knows how
to like like, you know, a snake charmer or something. ודתנא קמא,
ve-tana kama, and what does the תנא קמא tana kama feel? אגב
איצם מחתקי ליה, agav itzam mat-ke-lei, it might be nice you're a
snake charmer but if you're stepping on them and you're crowded with
them they're going to attack you. Okay. תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, נפל
לתוך כבשן האש. nafal le-toch kivshan ha-esh.
Now we go from Daniel to Chananya, Mishael, and Azaryah. You're thrown
into a fiery furnace. מעידים עליו, me'idim alav, then you can testify
he definitely died. ליורה מלאה יין ושמן, le-yora me-le'a yayin va-shemen,
if it's into a pot, you know, a huge vat filled with
boiling hot
wine and oil, מעידים עליו, me'idim alav, boiling hot. Well, we'll see.
יורה yora normally means a pot on a fire and we'll be
clear from the next line anyway. You can testify because you know
he he burn whatever it sca- whatever it will totally have. burn
him to death. Okay. משום רבי עקיבא אמרו Mishum Rabbi Akiva amru
ששמן מעידים עליו, she-shemen me'idim alav,
oil you can testify, I mean, you do not want to be
in a pot of boiling oil, מפני שהוא מבעיר. mipnei she-hu maveer.
So the way רש"י Rashi explains it is you're dumped into this
pot of oil, the oil splashes on the fire and feeds the
fire. של יין, shel yayin, but if it's wine, again, quite fascinating
that they would boil wine, like nowadays we do that to make
it, you know, מבושל, mevushal, which ruins the wine. So anyway, fascinating
that they would do it. If it was wine, אין מעידים עליו
ein me'idim alav מפני שהוא מכבה, mipnei she-hu mechabeh,
because when you are dumped into the pot of wine, the wine
splashes on the fire and extinguishes it, or at least cools it
off a little enough for you to escape maybe. אמרו לו, amru
lo, they said to him, תחילה הוא מכבה וסופו מבעיר. techila hu
mechabeh ve-sofo maveer. It might initially douse it a little bit, but
then the fire will, you know, will reignite
and therefore we can still assume he died. Okay, so those are
scenarios that are not water scenarios, but again, cases in which you
do not actually have a body and you're still allowed to make
certain assumptions because of the circumstances that you saw the person in
when you could assume that there was no reasonable way he could
have escaped. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir, מעשה באחד שנפל לבור
גדול, ma'aseh be-echad she-nafal le-vor gadol, a person fell into a big
well and he survived for three days. So therefore, רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says I'm not willing to make any ruling if I don't
see a body. תניא, Tanya, it's written in a ברייתא, Baraita, אמרו
לו לרבי מאיר, amru lo le-Rabbi Meir, they said to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, אין מזכירין מעשה נסים. ein mazkirin ma'aseh nissim. You can't
bring miracles as evidence. We have to make rules based on normal
circumstances. If somebody miraculously survived for three days, that's not going to
affect our legal standards. So מה מעשה נסים, ma ma'aseh nissim, what
was the miracle? Now you'd think, well, what do you mean? The
miracle is that people can't survive, but רש"י Rashi sort of says,
well, in addition to the discussion that we're having, which is the
one about like that whether, you know, people can go underwater and
somehow manage to survive, it sounds like there was some other thing
that was going on here. So what was the other fact that
they were saying like, oh, this would be miraculous? אילימא דלא אכל
ולא אישתי, Ilema de-lo achal ve-lo ishti,
he didn't eat for three days and he survived, והכתיב, ve-haktiv, 'צומו
עלי ואל תאכלו ואל תשתו שלשת ימים', 'tzomu alai ve-al tochlu ve-al
tishtu shloshet yamim',
right? We know people can starve for three days and survive. אלא
דלא ניים, Ella de-lo nayim, but that he didn't sleep, that he
managed to stay awake. I don't know how we know that, I
guess if he had fallen asleep then the water definitely he definitely
would have died because of he was in the well or the
water or whatever. דאמר רבי יוחנן, De-amar Rabbi Yochanan, שבועה שלא אישן
שלשה ימים, shvuah she-lo ishan shlosha yamim, מלקין אותו ויישן
לאלתר. malkin oto ve-yishan le-alter. Somebody takes an oath not to sleep
for three days, it's definitely a שבועת שוא, shvuat shav, there's no
way he'll be able to fulfill it, so you give him lashes
and therefore he's allowed to sleep right away because the oath isn't
binding, but he gets lashes because it was a false oath, it
was a שבועת שוא shvuat shav because he definitely couldn't fulfill it.
רבי מאיר מאי טעמא, Rabbi Meir mai ta'ama,
so what would רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir respond? How could he explain
that the guy could have slept without it being miraculous? אמר רב
כהנא, Amar Rav Kahana, כיפין על גבי כיפין הוו, kifin al gabi
kifin havu,
maybe that there were ledges in this well which allowed him to
put himself on a ledge and to sleep. I really don't understand
this at all, like why don't we just say it's miraculous that
he survived in the water for three days? Are we assuming there's
water or not? I mean if we're talking about oceans and water,
presumably we are. I mean רש"י Rashi says
מעשה נסים, ma'aseh nissim, אפילו אינו מת מחמת המים היה לו למות
מחמת דבר אחר. afilu eino met machmat ha-mayim haya lo lamut machmat
davar acher. But why, so why are the Rabbis insisting, oh, there
was another miracle? Why can't they just say that anyway surviving three
days in water is itself a miracle? So I don't understand that,
and then I also don't understand what the idea is about sleeping.
How do we know that he couldn't have fallen asleep and still
survived? Why is it assumed that if he fell asleep he definitely
would have died? Anyway, so he said that there were somehow various
types of ledges that allowed him to sleep. ורבנן, Ve-rabbanan, and the
Rabbis say, דשישא הוו, de-shisha havu, those were like, you know, marble,
they were smooth, so there's no way that he could have, you
know, slept on them without slipping off of them. ורבי מאיר Ve-Rabbi
Meir says, אי אפשר דלא משרך וניים, ee efshar de-lo misrach ve-nayim,
it would be impossible that he could not, you know, hold on
to a little piece, a little, a little indentation and manage to
lean on it and to sleep. I really don't have any idea
what we're talking about. Okay, moving on. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, our
Rabbis
taught: מעשה
בבתו, ma'aseh be-vito, a famous story with the daughter של נחוניא חופר
שיחין. shel Nechunya Chofer Shichin. נחוניא Nechunya
that was
who dug wells for the עולי בבל. Olei Bavel. This was his
big contribution to the ציבור, tzibbur, that he dug all these wells
for people that came up for עולי לרגל. Olei Le-Regel. And there
was a story with his daughter שנפלה לבור גדול, she-nafla le-vor gadol,
that he fell, she fell into a big well, exactly the thing
that he had been doing to contribute to the ציבור tzibbur all
his life, his daughter falls into this well. ובאו והודיעו לרבי חנינה
בן דוסא, U-vau ve-hodi'u le-Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa, they came and told
רבי חנינה בן דוסא. Rabbi Chanina ben Dosa. שעה ראשונה אמר להם
שלום, Sha'ah rishona amar lahem shalom, first hour he said to them,
look, you know, everything is fine because people can survive one hour.
שניה אמר להם שלום, Shniya amar lahem shalom, second hour he said
to them it's fine, it's fine. שלישית, Shlishit, third hour, by that
it was assessed that nobody would be able to survive three hours.
It's so funny that three hours it's assumed people can't survive, you
know, before we're talking about three days. Anyway, אמר להם עלתה, amar
lahem alta, he said to them by now she must have been
saved, right? Because if she wasn't saved, the alternative would be that
she'd be dead. So by now it must be that she was
saved. So אמר לה בתי מי העלך, amar la, 'biti mi he'elach',
so and actually and so it was the case, okay. And then
so he said to her, 'my daughter, who brought you up, how
did you survive?' אמרה לו, amra lo, she said to him, זכר
של רחלים נזדמן לי... zachar shel rachelim nizdamen li... There was a
certain ram וזקן מנהיגו vezaken manhigo and an old man was leading
it. So רש"י Rashi says this was אברהם Avraham and the ram
was the ram of יצחק. Yitzchak. Okay? אמרו לו, amru lo, so
they now went that so that's what he's reputedly what's his name
נחוניא Nechunya said to his daughter. So now they went and they
told רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina who knew that she had survived and
they went and they said to him נביא אתה, navi ata, you
must be a prophet, you knew that somehow she was miraculously saved.
אמר להם, amar lahem, he said to them, לא נביא אנכי ולא
בן נביא אנכי, lo navi anochi velo ben navi anochi, I'm not
a prophet or the son of a prophet, אלא דבר שהצדיק מתעסק
בו, ela davar she-ha-tzadik mit'asek bo, I assume that something that this
righteous person had devoted his life to, digging wells for, you know,
for the ציבור, tzibur, יכשל בו זרעו, yikashel bo zar'o, that should
be the thing that his, you know, his children his child should
stumble as a result, should die as a result of a well?
That was exactly what he had contributed his life to, so it
must have been something miraculous would have come and saved her. אמר
רבי אבא, amar Rabbi Abba, אף על פי כן, af al pi
chen, so you know that's the fascinating now the juxtaposition because here's
this like everything works out in the world and comes רבי אבא
Rabbi Abba says nevertheless מת בנו בצמא, met b'no ba-tzama, his son
died out of thirst. Now of course he devoted his life for
digging wells so people would have water and his son died out
of thirst. שנאמר, she-ne'emar, right, וסביביו נסערה מאד, u-svivav nis'ara me'od, around
him is great like a great whirlwind, which the דרשה drasha is
מלמד שהקדוש ברוך הוא מדקדק עם סביביו, melamed she-ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu medakdek
im svivav, God is careful with those that surround him, כחוט השערה,
ke-chut ha-se'ara, so נסערה, nis'ara, like a hair like like a strand
of hair. He's hyper-exacting with those that are close to him so
therefore of course the point being that since presumably for some sin
of נחוניא Nechunya the exacting and the punishment was that his child
died, which also gets into sort of rabbinic theology about that. רבי
חנינא אמר מהכא, Rabbi Chanina amar me-hacha, אל נערץ בסוד קדושים רבה
ונורא על כל סביביו, El na'aratz be-sod kedoshim raba ve-nora al kol
svivav, God is awesome, awe-inspiring by those that are around him, so
there's a particular sense of being exacting. Now of course the question
here is but what about the points that okay it's one thing
that God is exacting and it's one thing that the גמרא Gemara
is saying that you know children are punished for the sins of
the father, but what about the point that אותו דבר שהצדיק נצטער
בו? oto davar she-ha-tzadik nitzta'er bo? I mean he was מצטער mitzta'er
that people should have water. So תוספות Tosafot tries to reconcile it.
תוספות Tosafot says אף על פי כן מת בנו בצמא, af al
pi chen met b'no ba-tzama, תוספות Tosafot says מכל מקום לא הוי
דבר שנצטער בו הצדיק שלא עשה הבור. mi-kol makom lo havei davar
she-nitzta'er bo ha-tzadik she-lo asa ha-bor. At least it wasn't like the
very same well that he dug his daughter fell into. Okay even
though his whole life was devoted towards making sure people have water.
So it's interesting though you know on the one hand it's obviously
like disturbing this idea about children dying for the sins of the
fathers, I mean once explicitly but implicitly, but on the other hand
it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara does not allow itself to rest
on like a type of a oh everything works out, you know,
if you're a צדיק, tzadik, you know, you know, you'll you'll never
suffer as a result, you know, whatever happened you know to all
the people that they're going on some you know on some mission
of mercy and they you know die in a car crash or
something. So you know the גמרא Gemara sort of has this like
harsh juxtaposition like you know the world isn't so simple, things don't
always work out that way. Alright. So anyway that was the end
of that so but we do have this idea that we go
by יש להם סוף, yesh lahem sof, we can marry off even
without a body, in other situations we can marry off without a
body and as was alluded to and we're going to see again
as we get to the next משנה Mishna and גמרא, Gemara, that
what's not at all in the משנה Mishna but the גמרא Gemara
just drops in passing is that even when you're not supposed to
marry off the wife because you can't definitely assume the person has
died, בדיעבד be-di'avad she can stay married. Okay the question always is
like what's the limit of that, like how you know you know
how much evidence do you need to say בדיעבד be-di'avad it's okay.
Let's take a look at the משנה. Mishna. אפילו שמע מן הנשים,
afilu shama min ha-nashim, now we're going to get from one person
appearing in court and testifying as a formal act of testimony to
another enormous חידוש chiddush in these הלכות, halachot, right, which is hearsay
evidence. Nobody is even coming A, nobody is saying I directly saw,
it's just you know one person said to another person and so
on. Or maybe not so much עד מפי עד, ed mi-pi ed,
that's maybe not as explicit, but certainly it's something that's just said
in passing and not in any context of formal testimony. Okay. So
אפילו שמע מן הנשים אומרות מת איש פלוני דיו. afilu shama min
ha-nashim omrot met ish ploni dayo. Even if they heard from women
saying so-and-so died, that's enough. Now partly it's a חידוש chiddush of
women, maybe you would have thought that they only believe the wife,
you know, they wouldn't believe another woman because normally they don't accept
women as as as as witnesses. Of course that was pretty explicit
before because it also said you can't believe a woman for a
sister-in-law, mother-in-law, etc. So it was pretty implicit that you could accept
that right exactly. So here the point is not women, the point
is that it's not like a formal act of testifying. So רבי
יהודה אומר אפילו שמע מן התינוקות אומרים הרי אנו הולכים לספוד ולקבור
את איש פלוני. Rabbi Yehuda omer afilu shama min ha-tinokot omrim harei
anu holchim lispod velikbor et ish ploni. Even if you hear from
you know infants, not infants, children saying, so even somebody that's like
not of age that you might think you need an adult to
be able to trust what they're saying is true, here you have
children that are saying hey we're going to go to somebody's funeral,
eulogize and bury him. בין שנתכוון בין שאינו מתכוון, bein she-nitkaven bein
she-eino mitkaven, whether the people are intending to testify or not. Okay,
בין שמתכוון בין שאינו מתכוון. Bein she-mitkaven bein she-eino mitkaven. רבי יהודה
בן בבא אומר, Rebbi Yehuda ben Bava omer, ישראל אף על פי
שהוא מתכוון. Yisrael af al pi she-hu mitkaven. ובעובדי כוכבים אם היה
מתכוון אין עדותו עדות. U-v'ovdei chochavim im haya mitkaven ein eduto edut.
So this is interesting whether it's אף על פי af al pi
or עד שיהיה מכוון, ad she-yehei mechaven, okay, but so רבי יהודה
בן בבא Rebbi Yehuda ben Bava is saying let's start with a
non-Jew, so he's saying by a non-Jew, if he's intentionally testifying, it's
not good, right? For a non-Jew there's this concern that he might
intentionally be trying to make trouble, so it's only if he's saying
it completely innocently and in passing, then we can assume, oh, you
know, he just said it in passing, obviously he's not, you know,
there's nothing nefarious going on, so we can trust it. Okay, when
he's saying it intentionally we're concerned that he's trying to intentionally mess
people up. So that's the classic category of מסיח לפי תומו. masiach
lefi tumo. Somebody just talking in all innocence, okay, which comes from
a skepticism or suspicion in terms of the testimony of non-Jews. Now
what does he say about the Jew? There's two very different גרסות
girsot here. Our גרסה girsa is even if he's intending. So then
it fits with the idea, you know, a Jew if we're basically
assuming that intending is worse interestingly because maybe they're trying to intentionally
mislead. So the read even if he's intending would assume the same
point by a Jew. Intending to testify is always considered possibly worse,
maybe the person has some other agenda. But by a Jew even
intending is okay, at least we're keeping them by the same standard,
right? That intending is considered to be possibly worse. The other גרסה
girsa if you look at the side is עד שיהיה מכוון, ad
she-yehei mechaven, the exact opposite. Right, by a Jew we're going to
demand a normal act of testimony. Come to court and consciously testify,
right? Just saying something in passing is not enough, you have to
take, you have to take the full weight of the act that
you're doing and you have to present yourself in court and intentionally
testify, that gives it the full weight. Saying it in passing isn't
enough. Okay, but then it becomes very funny. So saying in passing
by a Jew isn't enough because he's not taking it seriously enough,
but for a non-Jew it is. So anyway it really shows you
how far we're willing to go in order to accept things that
normally would not constitute as testimony in these cases. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. ודילמא לא אזלו, Ve-dilma lo azlu, what
do you mean they're saying we're going to somebody's funeral? Maybe they
didn't go and maybe they never actually saw, and maybe by the
time they got there they found out oh, funeral's cancelled, the guy
actually turned out to be alive. So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel דקאמרי de-kamri they say, they didn't say
we're going, they said הרי אנו באים מלספוד ומלקבור את איש פלוני,
Harei anu baim milispod u-milikvor et ish ploni, we're returning from the
guy's funeral, את איש פלוני. et ish ploni. ודילמא קמצא בעלמא שכיב
ליה ואסקו ליה על שמיה, Ve-dilma kamtza be-alma shachiv lei ve-asku lei
al shemei, so these are kids saying it, so maybe they had
a little gerbil, actually a קמצא kamtza is like רש"י Rashi says
it's a grasshopper or something that they called, you know, Fred Smith,
a little grasshopper called Fred Smith. So we're say we're coming back
from Fred Smith's funeral, they mean their little pet grasshopper's funeral. So
how do you know that it's the guy we identify as Fred
Smith? ואמרי Ve-amri because they say they don't just say we're coming
from so and so's funeral, they say כך וכך רבנן הוו התם,
kach ve-kach rabanan havu hatam, oh there were like so many rabbis
there, כך וכך ספדניא הוו התם, kach ve-kach safdanaya havu hatam, there
were so many eulogizers there. So they give enough detail that we
can assume that it's true. Now again notice what the גמרא's Gemara
doing, right? The simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is here before
the גמרא Gemara seemed to be expanding the cases that we had
in the משנה, Mishnah, here it seems to be narrowing it a
little bit, clarifying that it can't be totally hearsay, we need at
least the content of the testimony, you know, it can't be like
totally in passing, we need the contents to be something that we
can know, you know, what it means and we can know that
it's, you know, specific enough. ובעובדי כוכבים אם היה מתכוון. U-v'ovdei chochavim
im haya mitkaven. Okay. Non-Jew until they are, if he's intending, no
good. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel לא
שנו אלא שנתכוון להתיר. Lo shanu ela she-nitkaven le-hatir. And now we're
going to go to try to again expand the cases where we
can believe. Even though the משנה Mishnah says that if he's intending
we can't accept it, we're going to define intending very narrowly. Only
if he's coming to court intending to say I want you to
make the, allow his wife to remarry. אבל נתכוון להעיד, Aval nitkaven
le-haid, if he's coming to testify without explicitly doing it for the
purpose of allowing the woman to remarry, עדותו עדות eduto edut we
accept it. Now that's really splitting a hair, because why else would
you testify about a man's wife unless, you know, it was about
letting her remarry? So the גמרא Gemara says היכי ידינן, Heichi yadinan,
and how anyway are we going to know which one is his
intent? So אמר רב יוסף Amar Rav Yosef בא לבית דין ואמר
איש פלוני מת השיאו את אשתו, ba le-veit din ve-amar ish ploni
met hasiyu et ishto, if he came to court and said, hey
you know what, so and so died you should let his wife
remarry, זהו נתכוון להתיר. zehu nitkaven le-hatir. That's when he's coming explicitly.
To let her remarry, and then we say he's coming to cause
trouble and we don't accept it. מת סתם, meis stam, if he
just says to court, hey, you should know so and so is
dead, and he doesn't mention the wife, זהו נתכוין לעדות, zehu nitkavein
le'eidus, that's acceptable. So again, we have now created, we have taken
the case of the משנה, Mishna, נתכוין, nitkavein, and we've made it
extremely tiny. How many people are going to explicitly say, so and
so is dead, you should marry off his wife? So he'll just
say so and so is dead. So we've basically shrunk the case
to the משנה Mishna to be a very tiny case. איתמר נמי
itmar nami was also taught this way. אמר ריש לקיש שלושה הן
שנתכוין להתיר אבל נתכוין להעיד עדותו עדות. Amar Reish Lakish shlosha hen
shenitkavein lehatir aval nitkavein leha'id eiduso eidus. So Reish Lakish said only
if he's coming to make her explicitly make her permissible. אמר ליה
רבי יוחנן, Amar lei Rabbi Yochanan, and רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan objected.
לא כך היה מעשה באושיא בריבי, lo kach haya ma'aseh be'Oshaya Beribbi,
wasn't there a story with this person called אושיא בריבי, Oshaya Beribbi,
רבי Rabbi is like an honorific, שהתריס כנגד שמונים וחמישה זקנים, shehisris
keneged shemonim vechamisha zekeinim, that he sort of came into conflict with
eighty-five elders? אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to them, לא שנו
אלא שנתכוין להתיר אבל נתכוין להעיד עדותו עדות. lo shanu ela shenitkavein
lehatir aval nitkavein leha'id eiduso eidus. It's only if he's explicitly coming
to make his wife permissible, we don't accept the intentional testimony of
a non-Jew, but if he's just to testify, it's okay. And so
that was your position, Reish Lakish, ולא הודו לו חכמים, velo hodu
lo chachamim, but these eighty-five sages disagreed with him. So okay, I
know there's a position out there, but that's wrong. We say that
anytime it's intentional, it's not accepted. אלא מתניתין דעובד כוכבים דנתכוין אין
עדותו עדות היכי משכחת לה? ela masnisin de'oved kochavim denitkavein ein eiduso
eidus heichi mashkachas lah? So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, you,
רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, that you're saying that any intentional testimony is
not acceptable, what would be an example of non-intentional testimony? Which is
such a funny question. I mean, the גמרא Gemara gave cases, people
are just schmoozing. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. במסיח לפי
תומו. bemesiach lefi tumo. Yeah, guy just talking in all his innocence,
that's what the case is. כי ההוא, ki hahu, like a case
דהוה קאמר ואזיל, dahavei ka'amar ve'azil, he was coming and saying, מן
איכא בי חיוואי מן איכא בי חיוואי, man ika bei Chivai man
ika bei Chivai, who is from the family of חיוואי? Chivai? שכיב
חיוואי, shachiv Chivai, you should know that he's died. In that case,
ואנסבה רב יוסף לדביתהו, ve'ansivah Rav Yosef lidevinhu, רב יוסף Rav Yosef
let his wife remarry. So which is also interesting, he wasn't just
schmoozing with a friend and we overheard it. He's like, I want
to tell his wife that he's died. And that's considered מסיח לפי
תומו mesiach lefi tumo because he's not coming to court and testifying.
He's just doing a good neighborly thing and informing the wife. That's
מסיח לפי תומו. mesiach lefi tumo. So even in רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan's read that any נתכוין nitkavein is no good, we're still explaining
נתכוין, nitkavein, you know, in a somewhat narrow way. Like he's explicitly
intentionally telling the wife, I want you to know your husband is
dead. That's מסיח לפי תומו. mesiach lefi tumo. The only נתכוין nitkavein
would be he's coming to court and saying, I want to, you
know, I want to testify that the husband is dead. One minute.
ההוא דהוה קאמר ואזיל, hahu dahavei ka'amar ve'azil, a person was going
and saying, ווי לה לפרשתא דזריזא, vai lah leparshata dezeriza, woe to
the, you know, the zealous sort of soldier, דהוה בפומבדיתא דשכיב, dahavei
bePumbedita deshachiv, that was in פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, that he died. And so
he's just moaning somebody's death. So that's a more מסיח לפי תומו.
mesiach lefi tumo. He was just, you know, bewailing somebody's death. ואנסבה
רב יוסף ואיתימא רבא לדביתהו, ve'ansivah Rav Yosef ve'isima Rava lidevinhu, and
רב יוסף Rav Yosef or רבא Rava married off the wife. ההוא
דהוה קאמר ואזיל, hahu dahavei ka'amar ve'azil, somebody was going and saying,
מן איכא בי חסא, man ika bei Chassa, who's from the family
of חסא? Chassa? טבע חסא, tava Chassa, חסא Chassa drowned. אמר רב
נחמן אלוקים, Amar Rav Nachman Elokim, is that really true? Oh my
god. אכלו כוורי לחסא, achlu kavrei leChassa, the fish have eaten חסא.
Chassa. So מדיבוריה דרב נחמן, mideiburei deRav Nachman, now since רב נחמן
Rav Nachman said it must be the fish have eaten חסא, Chassa,
not only do we see that he accepted the testimony of this
non-Jew who was speaking in innocence, but again, it's a water case,
right? So how do we know, was it מים שיש להם סוף
mayim sheyeish lahem sof or מים שאין להם סוף? mayim she'ein lahem
sof? So since he said the fish, you know, what is it,
you sleep with the fishes tonight? So since he said the fish
have eaten him, so therefore we assume that he was ruling that
he was dead. He wasn't concerned that he came up on another
shore. So based on that, מדיבוריה דרב נחמן אזלה דביתהו דחסא, mideiburei
deRav Nachman azlah devinhu deChassa, and here's your question, Michael, no ruling
in any court case, חסא Chassa's wife overheard רב נחמן Rav Nachman
said the fish are eating חסא, Chassa, and the wife went on
her own ואינסבא, ve'insava, and she got married, ולא אמרו לה ולא
מידי, velo amru lah velo midi, and nobody and nobody said anything
to her, before or after. אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, so
this is a big חידוש chiddush not only about a גוי מסיח
לפי תומו, goy mesiach lefi tumo, this is very important in terms
of ending our previous discussion. שמע מינה התם רבנן מים שאין להם
סוף אשה אסורה, shma mina hatam rabanan mayim she'ein lahem sof isha
asura, when we say if there's no edge to the water and
no body, the wife is forbidden, הני מילי לכתחילה, hani mili lechatchila,
that's only at the outset. אבל אי נסבא, aval i nasva, if
she got married, and here she got married without rabbinic sanction, right?
She heard the rabbi make some assumption, but you know what, even
the rabbi was speaking loosely, because legally we could not assume he
was dead, and she went ahead and she got remarried, לא מפקינן
לה מינה, lo mafkinan lah minah, we do not make her divorce
her new husband. איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri, and some say, אנסבה רב
נחמן לדביתהו, ansivah Rav Nachman lidevinhu, רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, you know,
gave a פסק psak to marry the wife. אמר חסא גברא רבה
איתיה, Amar Chassa gavra rabba isei, like we said before, חסא Chassa
was a great man, famous, אם איתא דסליק קלא אית ליה למילתא,
im issa desalik kala is lei lemilsa, if he would have come
up from another edge, we would have heard about it. And the
גמרא Gemara says, ולא היא, velo hi, that's not true, that's not
a basis for פוסק paskening that it's okay. לא שנא גברא רבה
ולא שנא לא גברא רבה, lo shna gavra rabba velo shna lo
gavra rabba, doesn't matter famous or not famous, the... Only בדיעבד b'di
eved it's okay, לכתחילה lichatchila no, not לכתחילה. lichatchila. So amazingly the
גמרא Gemara said besides defining מתכוין miskavein even according to רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan somewhat more narrowly, intentionally informing the wife is not called
מתכוין, miskavein, it's called מסיח לפי תומו, masiach l'fi tumo, but more
importantly the גמרא Gemara says that even when we say you're not
allowed to marry off the wife, if she went ahead and she
remarried, she could stay married. Of course, if the husband hasn't shown
up, and the question would be how thin does the evidence have
to be to allow it בדיעבד, b'di eved, but this is obviously
a very big חידוש chiddush and all of this is part of
these leniencies that we are doing to allow this woman to remarry.
Okay. Yes.